Guide to the Arthur I. Bloomfield papers, 1927-1995 and undated RL.00122
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Arthur I. Bloomfield papers
1927-1995 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bloomfield, Arthur I. (Arthur Irving)
RL.00122
12 Linear Feet
The papers of university professor and economist Arthur Bloomfield consist chiefly of research files from his job as economist at the Federal Reserve Bank of New York, 1941-1958, professional and academic correspondence received or written from 1931 to 1995, research notes on various topics in international finance, notes for his university classes on the history of economic thought, and research files on the pre-1914 gold standard. The papers document Bloomfield's career as economist and professor of economics, with special emphasis on his work as economic consultant for the United States federal government, particularly for the New York Federal Reserve Bank, and for the governments of post-World War II South Korea and Indochina. His chief areas of research activity focused on international banking, evaluating foreign aid programs, the pre-1914 gold standard, and economic development in the U.K. and British Commonwealth countries (including the British West Indies), and economy and banking in Malaysia, the Congo, and Zaire. Substantial materials on the history of economic thought can be found in Bloomfield's teaching files.
Approximately 7200 items
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Correspondence, Incoming and Outgoing; Federal Reserve Bank of New York; Pre-1914 Gold Standard; History of Economic Thought; Research Files; and Other Papers.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1914, Oct. 2 Born Arthur Irving Bloomfield in Montreal, Canada.
1931 Entered McGill University on scholarship after graduating first out of 900 students in the Province of Quebec high school leaving examinations.
1935 B.A. (Economics and Political Science), McGill University.
1936 M.A. (Economics and Political Science), McGill University. Thesis: Canadian Wheat Marketing Policy, 1929-1936.
1940, Autumn-1941 Research Assistant to Prof. Oskar Morgenstern, Princeton University. Collected and analyzed international financial data for major industrial countries before 1914 and in the 1920s.
1941-1958 Federal Reserve Bank of New York: Economist, Research Dept. 1941-1947; Chief of Balance of Payments Division, 1947-53; Senior Economist, 1953-58.
1942 Ph.D. (Economics), University of Chicago.
1944-1945 Consultant to Foreign Economic Administration, Washington, D.C.
1945 Acquired U.S. Citizenship.
1949, Sept.-1950, Mar. Advisor, Bank of Korea and Korean Ministry of Finance, Seoul, South Korea, on behalf of the Economic Cooperation Administration.
1950 Publication of Capital Imports and the American Balance of Payments, 1934-39 (University of Chicago Press), based on doctoral dissertation.
1951, Dec.-1952, Apr. Financial Advisor, United Nations Civil Assistance Command and the United Nations Korean Reconstruction Agency, in Pusan, South Korea.
1953, Feb. Member, four-person team sent to the Associated States of Indochina by the Mutual Security Administration to evaluate U.S. foreign aid program to that area.
1953, Autumn Senior Economist, Professional Staff of the (Randall) Commission on Foreign Economic Policy, U.S. Government, Washington, D.C.
1954, Oct.-1955, Jan. Consultant, U.S. Foreign Operations Administration, Indochina.
1956, Nov. and 1960, Aug. Consultant, International Cooperation Administration, in Seoul, South Korea.
1957-1958 Year-long research trip visiting 12 European central banks (six months at Bank of England) on a Rockefeller grant, conducting research on the international gold standard before 1914.
1958-1985 Professor of Economics, University of Pennsylvania.
1959 Published Monetary Policy under the International Gold Standard, 1880-1914 (Fed. Reserve Bank NY).
1961, Jan. Consultant, Institute of Social and Economic Research, University College of the West Indies, Jamaica and Trinidad.
1963 Published Short-term Capital Movements under the Pre-1914 Gold Standard (Princeton Univ. Press).
1964, Sept.-Dec. Consultant, Central Bank of Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur, on behalf of the Ford Foundation.
1966, Aug.-Sept. and 1967, June Consultant, U.S. Agency for International Development, in the Democratic Republic of Congo.
1968 Published Patterns of Fluctuation in International Investment Before 1914 (Princeton Univ. Press).
1974-1975 Research in London for article Adam Smith and the Theory of International Trade.
1978-1998 Member, Managing Board of Editors, Journal of Post Keynesian Economics.
1985-1998 Professor Emeritus of Economics, University of Pennsylvania.
1998, Oct. 6 Died in Washington, D.C.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Arthur I. Bloomfield papers were received by the Special Collections Library as a gift from Professor Bloomfield in 1996. Funding for the processing of this collection was provided by Professor Bloomfield.
Collection Overview
The papers of university professor and economist Arthur Bloomfield span the period from 1927 to 1995. They consist chiefly of research files from his job as economist at the Federal Reserve Bank of New York, 1941-1958, professional and academic correspondence received or written from 1931 to 1995, research notes on various topics in international finance, notes for his university classes on the history of economic thought, and research files on the pre-1914 gold standard. The papers document Bloomfield's career as economist and professor of economics, with special emphasis on his work as economic consultant for the United States federal government, particularly for the New York Federal Reserve Bank, and for the governments of post-World War II South Korea and Indochina. His chief areas of research activity focused on international banking, evaluating foreign aid programs, the pre-1914 gold standard, and economic development in the U.K. and British Commonwealth countries (including the British West Indies), and economy and banking in Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur, the Congo, and Zaire. Substantial materials on the history of economic thought can be found in Bloomfield's teaching files. The collection is comprised of six series: Correspondence Series, Incoming and Outgoing; Federal Reserve Bank of New York Series; Pre-1914 Gold Standard Series; History of Economic Thought Series; Research Files Series; and Miscellaneous Series.
The Correspondence Series, Incoming and Outgoing, contains letters received or written by Bloomfield over the period 1931 to 1995. Arranged in folders chronologically, this substantive collection of letters lends insight into Bloomfield's professional and academic life.
The Federal Reserve Bank of New York Series contains material pertaining to Bloomfield's first career, spanning 17 years, as an economist at the New York Federal Reserve Bank. For that position he wrote a number of research memoranda and in-house articles on a wide range of international finance topics. Before World War II he wrote mostly on economic developments in the U.K. and British Commonwealth countries, but after the war his research memoranda involved a broader range of topics.
The Pre-1914 Gold Standard Series contains research notes for an intended book on the functioning of the international gold standard, 1880-1914. Bloomfield embarked on a year-long research trip to Europe in 1957 on a Rockefeller grant, visiting twelve European central banks, including the Bank of England where he spent over six months. In the end, he did not complete the book, but did write three substantial monographs from his notes: Monetary Policy under the International Gold Standard, 1880-1914 (Fed. Reserve Bank NY, 1959); Short-term Capital Movements under the Pre-1914 Gold Standard (Princeton Univ. Press, 1963); and Patterns of Fluctuation in International Investment before 1914 (Princeton Univ. Press, 1968). Although these books are not in the collection, this series contains one file folder for many countries or geographical areas, including: Switzerland, U.S.A., Sweden, Norway, Italy, Australia, New Zealand, South Africa, India, Egypt, France, Canada, U.K., Japan, Germany, Finland, Denmark, Russia, Belgium, Netherlands, Austria, and Hungary.
The History of Economic Thought Series is an extensive collection of files on diverse topics in the history of economic thought. After 1974 Bloomfield's research became increasingly devoted to the history of economic thought, and he taught both graduate and undergraduate level classes on the subject at the University of Pennsylvania.
The Research Files Series contains research notes associated with various overseas assignments and trips. Over the period 1949-1984, Bloomfield made numerous trips to developing countries as a consultant, in some cases helping to establish the Central Bank (e.g. South Korea), or in other cases evaluating foreign aid programs to those areas (e.g. Indochina). In addition to notes made in preparation for, and during, these assignments, this series also contains notes for several articles (published and unpublished), speeches, and conferences.
The bulk of the Miscellaneous Series consists of papers from Bloomfield's undergraduate days at McGill University, including one paper written in 1937 for Frank Knight's ECO 305 class at the University of Chicago, titled Thorstein Veblen and his Analysis of Business Enterprise.
United States. Army. Korea Civil Assistance Command; Banks and banking -- Congo (Democratic Republic); Banks and banking -- West Indies; Banks and banking -- England; Banks and banking -- South Korea; Economic assistance, American-Indochina; Economic history; Economists -- Correspondence; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Gold standard -- History; International finance; Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher); Congo (Democratic Republic) -- Economic conditions; Great Britain -- Economic conditions -- 20th century; Korea (South) -- Economic conditions; Malaysia -- Economic conditions; West Indies -- Economic conditions; Zaire -- Economic conditions; Bloomfield, Arthur I. (Arthur Irving); Federal Reserve Bank of New York
- Correspondence, Incoming and Outgoing, 1931-1995
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes all correspondence received by and written by Professor Bloomfield concerning academic and other professional matters. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Incoming, 1931-1995 (51 folders) (Box 1)
  - Outgoing, 1944-1948 (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Outgoing, 1949-1995 (46 folders) (Box 2)
- Federal Reserve Bank of New York, 1941-1958
  Contains Bloomfield's research memoranda (short papers or articles which he wrote on a diverse range of topics) and reports written for his job as an economist with the Federal Reserve Bank of New York.
  - Research Memoranda, 1941-1944 (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - Research Memoranda, 1944-1950, 11 folders (Box 3A)
  - Research Memoranda, 1951-1958; 10 folders (Box 3B)
- Pre-1914 Gold Standard, 1945-1966 and undated
  Contains material for Bloomfield's intended book on the functioning of the international gold standard.
  - One file folder each on: Sweden, Switzerland, and U.S.A., 1903-1961 (Box 9)
  - One file folder each on: Norway, Italy, Australia- New Zealand, South Africa, India, Egypt and miscellaneous European and Far Eastern Countries ( ca. 1957-1966) (Box 3C)
  - One file folder each on: France, Canada, United Kingdom, Japan, Germany, Finland, Denmark, Russia, Belgium, Netherlands, Austria, Hungary Bibliography, undated (Box 4)
  - Oversize materials on Cananda (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Oversize materials: Readings and Statistics (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Summary Country Notes, ca. 1958 (Box 4)
  - Pre-1914 Short-term Capital Movements, 1957-1962 (Box 4)
  - Some general readings on the Gold Standard especially before 1914, 1945-1958 (Box 4)
- History of Economic Thought, 1974-1985 and undated
  This series contains class lectures, readings, and other teaching materials on the history of economic thought. Arranged in original random order.
  - Classical economists in general, undated (Box 4)
  - Physiocrats and Turgot, undated (Box 4)
  - David Ricardo (Box 4)
  - J. S. Mill and J. E. Cairns, undated (Box 4)
  - Marxist Economics (Box 4)
  - Senior, Say, Bentham, undated (Box 5)
  - The Austrians: Menger, Bohm-Bawerk, Wierser, undated (Box 5)
  - Thomas Malthus and Lord Lauderdale, undated (Box 5)
  - Historical School and Institutionalists, undated (Box 5)
  - Gevons and the Marginal Revolution (Box 5)
  - Walras and Pareto, undated (Box 5)
  - Alfred Marshall, undated (Box 5)
  - Cournot, Gossen, Dupont, von Thunen (Box 5)
  - Wicksell, Schumpeter, Fisher.. ., undated (Box 5)
  - J.B. Clark and Marginal Productivity, undated (Box 5)
  - 19th C. British Views on Trade and Growth, undated (8 folders) (Box 5)
  - Notes and Readings on article " Adam Smith and Theory of International Trade," undated (Box 5)
  - Ancients and Schoolmen, ca. 1983 (Box 5)
  - Mercantilists and Galiani, Hume, Cantillon, Pelty, Buisguilbaert, Stewart, ca. 1983 (Box 5)
  - Adam Smith, ca. 1985 (Box 5)
  - Some readings and notes on class lecture in the Theory of International trade, Part II, ca. 1975 (Box 5)
  - Some readings on Class Lectures in International Monetary Economics, ca. 1983 (Box 5)
  - Some lectures on History of Economic Thought, ca. 1980 (Box 5)
  - Some Lectures on History of Economic Thought, ca. 1980 (Box 6)
  - English Theories of Trade and Growth, 1700-1800, ca. 1983 (Box 6)
  - 19th C. British views on Emigration, Colonization, and Trade, ca. 1983 (Box 6)
  - 19th Century French theories on Foreign Trade (and Bibliography), ca.1983 (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Viner and Keynes and Macroeconomics, ca. late 1970s (Box 6)
  - Class Reading Lists and Examinations, 1974-1981 (Box 6)
- Research Files, 1940-1992 and undated, bulk 1948-1983
  Notes relating to overseas assignments, publications, and various other professional activities. Arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Report on the Congolese Zairian Monetary Reform, 1967 June (Box 6)
  - Work as an Assistant to Oskar Morgenstern on his National Bureau (Box 6)
  - Project on the Gold Standard, 1940 Sept.-1941 Nov. (Box 6)
  - Trip to London and Paris for Federal Reserve Bank of N.Y., 1948 Apr.-May (Box 6)
  - Memoranda Prepared for U.N. Civil Assistance Command, Korea and U.N. Reconstruction Agency, 1951 Dec.-1952 Mar. (Pusan, Korea) (Box 6)
  - Misc. Memoranda of Federal Reserve Bank N.Y., 1948-1956, 1950-1956 (Box 6)
  - Notes on two Trips to S. Korea, 1949-1950, 1951-1952 (Box 6)
  - Answers to Questions Submitted by the Bank of Korea, Pusan, 1952, 8 Feb. (Box 6)
  - Some Notes on my Work with the Randall Commission, 1953 (Box 6)
  - Paper delivered at NYU, "We Live in the World: An Analysis of International Balance of Payments Problems, Foreign Investment and Foreign Aid," 1953 Oct. (Box 6)
  - Missions to Indochina (Member of Wilbur Commission of 1953) (Box 6)
  - Assignments in the British West Indies and Colonial Monetary Systems, 1960-1961 (Box 6)
  - Discussion at Meeting of Association for Asian Studies, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Notes on Monetary Targeting (in connection with 1963 unpublished report on Malaysia) (Box 6)
  - Country Summary Notes on my Princeton Study, No. 21, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Notes and Readings on my trade-theory survey article in the Annals 1969 (Box 6)
  - Report to Wilbur Commission on foreign aid to the Associated States of Cambodia, Laos, and Vietnam, 1953 (Box 6)
  - Fund Report on trip to England and France for Federal Reserve Bank of N.Y., 1948 (Box 6)
  - Notes on Speeches at NYU, Cornell, Waterloo, University of Melbourne, 1972 (Box 7A)
  - Official intervention in the foreign exchange market (notes for State Dept. Report), 1973-1977 (Box 7A)
  - Claremont Monetary Conference, 1978 October (Box 7A)
  - Speech on Korea (with notes) before Tuesday Korean Luncheon Meeting at Library of Congress, 1988, 19 Apr. (Box 7A)
  - Miscellaneous (from notes on Jacob Viner), 1972-1992 (Box 7A)
  - Central Banks and the State, 1979-1983 (Box 7A)
  - Memoranda written for Foreign Economic Administration and Federal Reserve Board, 1944-1945 (Box 7A)
  - Short-term Capital Movements before 1914: Notes on Princeton study ( ca. 1963) (Box 7A)
  - Notes and some statistics on my Princeton Study #21 (1968) (Box 7A)
  - Long Cycles in Foreign Investment before 1914 (Princeton Study #21), 1968 (Box 7B)
  - Marxism and Foreign Trade: Notes on an Uncompleted Project, ca. 1970 (Box 7B)
  - My comments about and notes on Bologna Conference, 1971 (Box 7B)
- Other Papers, 1927-1992 and undated
  Contains Bloomfield's undergraduate work at McGill University, including term papers, papers written for his extracurricular clubs, and speeches. Also contains a paper written in graduate school at the University of Chicago. Additional miscellaneous files include reprints of articles by Jacob Viner and obituaries of colleagues. Arranged in original random order.
  - Miscellaneous reports and papers by Bloomfield (7 folders): (Box 7B-8)
    - "The Economic Crisis and Commission Government in Newfoundland," 1935 (Box 7B-8)
    - The Single Tax: A Study in the Economics of Dissent, 1935 (Box 7B-8)
    - "The Bretton Woods Agreements," ca. 1943-1944, for Hillel Club (Box 7B-8)
    - Progress Already Made Towards World Recovery, 1934, for McGill Political Economy Club (Box 7B-8)
    - "What Can We Do for the Maritime Provinces?," 1935, written for McGill Political Economy Club (Box 7B-8)
    - "The Allegory in the First Book of the Fairie Queene by Edmund Spenser," undated (Box 7B-8)
    - The Canadian Wheat Problem, 1936 (Box 7B-8)
    - The Pluralistic Revolt in Politics, 1935 (Box 7B-8)
    - " Thorstein Veblen and his Analysis of Business Enterprise," 1937 (written for Frank Knight's ECO 305 class at U. of Chicago) (Box 7B-8)
  - Reprints of articles on deaths of prominent economists, 1973-1992 (Box 7B-8)
  - Sidney Weintraub's CV, 1977-1979 (Box 7B-8)
  - Sidney Weintraub's memorial service, 1983 (Box 7B-8)
  - Reprints of some articles of Jacob Viner, 1927-1962 (Box 7B-8)
  - Term papers and speeches from McGill and University of Chicago, 1933 (Box 7B-8)